Ludwig Jekels Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ludwig Jekels Papers 1892-1985 (bulk 1930-1952)
Jekels, Ludwig, 1867-1954
1,500 items
5 containers
1.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychoanalyst. Correspondence, lectures, subject files, and writings relating to Jekel’s work in the field of psychoanalysis and his writings on dreams, sleep, and wakefulness. Also includes correspondence and writings of Herbert Silberer.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Aichhorn, August, 1878-1949--Correspondence.; Bonaparte, Marie, Princess, 1882-1962--Correspondence.; Eissler, K. R. (Kurt Robert), 1908-1999--Correspondence.; Federn, Paul.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.; Jekels, Ludwig, 1867-1954.; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955--Correspondence.; Rank, Otto, 1884-1939--Correspondence.; Silberer, Herbert, 1882-1922. Herbert Silberer papers. 1919-1922.; Zilboorg, Gregory, 1890-1959--Correspondence.
Subjects
Dreams.; Psychoanalysis.; Sleep.; Wakefulness.
Occupations
Psychoanalysts.
Provenance
The papers of Ludwig Jekels, psychoanalyst and writer, were given to the Library of Congress by the Sigmund Freud Archives between 1984 and 1986. Some items were originally processed as part of the Sigmund Freud Papers, from which they have been transferred.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Ludwig Jekels are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1867 Born, Ludwig Jekeles, Austria
1892 Received medical degree, University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria
circa 1895 Founded sanitarium in Silesia for the treatment of nervous disorders
1903 Changed name to Ludwig Jekels
1905 Became a pupil of Sigmund Freud
circa 1915 1935 Practiced psychoanalysis in Vienna, Austria
1935 Moved to Sweden
1938 Immigrated to the United States
1954, Apr. 3 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ludwig Jekels (1867-1954) span the years 1892-1985, with the bulk of material dating from 1930 to 1952. The collection includes correspondence, lectures, subject files, and writings in German and English. Among the correspondents are August Aichhorn, Princess Marie Bonaparte, K. R. Eissler, Thomas Mann, Otto Rank, and Gregory Zilboorg. The lecture and writings files feature Jekels's work on dreams, sleep, and wakefulness, his collection of dream data from patients, and the response to one of his writings by Paul Federn. An autograph book dated 8 May 1936 contains the signatures of Thomas Mann and others who attend Mann's lecture "Freud und die Zukunft" at a banquet honoring Sigmund Freud on his eightieth birthday. The collection also includes original manuscripts and letters by writer Herbert Silberer, 1919-1922.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Aichhorn, August, 1936-1937, 1946-1950, undated (Box 1)
  - Bonaparte, Princess Marie, 1929-1940, 1953 (Box 1)
  - "B-C" miscellaneous, 1938-1954, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Eissler, K. R., 1947-1953 (Box 1)
  - "F" miscellaneous, 1931-1949 (Box 1)
  - "G" miscellaneous, 1943-1952 See also Closed (Box 1)
  - "H" miscellaneous, 1936-1951, undated (Box 1)
  - "J" miscellaneous, 1939-1952, undated See also Closed (Box 1)
  - "K-L" miscellaneous, 1940-1953, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Mann, Thomas, 1930 (Box 1)
  - "M" miscellaneous, 1939-1951, undated See also Closed (Box 1)
  - "N-O" miscellaneous, 1936-1954, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Rank, Otto, 1908-1911 (Box 1)
  - "R-W" miscellaneous, 1911-1952, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Zilboorg, Gregory, 1940 (Box 1)
- Lectures (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - In English, undated (Box 1)
    - In German, 1935-1937 (Box 1)
  - On dreams, probably given in Sweden or Germany, pre-1937 (Box 1)
  - "Psychoanalyse und Dialektik," 1940 (Box 1)
    - English translation (Box 1)
    - German drafts, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 1, Box 2)
  - "Über psychoanalytische Therapie," 1935 (Box 2)
  - "Vorlesungen über Traumarbeit," undated (Box 2)
- Miscellany, 1985, undated (Box 2)
- Subject file (Box 2)
  - Birthday greetings, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Freud, Sigmund, eightieth birthday celebration, 1936 (Box 2)
    - Autograph book (Box 2)
    - Comité für die Glückwunschadresse an Freud (Box 2)
  - Legal documents, diploma, and certificates, 1892-1903, 1940-1947 (Box 2)
  - Patient case file, Helene S. Frank, 1936-1938 (Box 2)
  - Silberer, Herbert, original manuscripts of writings and correspondence with Lili Tilgner, 1919-1922 (Box 3)
- Writings (Box 3)
  - "A Bioanalytical Contribution to the Problem of Sleep and Wakefulness," 1944 (Box 3)
    - Drafts and notes, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Federn, Paul, commentary on Jekel’s paper and draft of "Dream Under General Anesthesia," 1939 (Box 3)
  - Discussion of paper by Annie Reich, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Dream material of patients, collected by Jekels, 1936-1939, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - "In Memoriam--Sigmund Freud," 1939 (Box 3)
  - "Nachruf für Alexander Férenczi gehalten am 1 Juni 1933 im Akad. Verein für med Psychologie," 1933 (Box 3)
  - Notes and remarks, 1945, undated (Box 4)
  - Notes (Box 4)
    - On dreams, 1907 (Box 4)
    - On Shakespeare, undated (Box 4)
    - Scientific, undated (Box 4)
  - "Psychologie der Comödie," undated (Box 4)
  - Reminiscences of Freud, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Riddle of Shakespeare's Macbeth," undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - "Siegmund Freud, Der Mann und sein Werk," given at Freud's eightieth birthday celebration, Stockholm, Sweden, 1936, 1954 (Box 4)
- Closed (Box X1)
  - Correspondence (Box X1)
    - "G" miscellaneous, 1952, (Container 1) (Box X1)
    - "J" miscellaneous, 1939, (Container 1) (Box X1)
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1941, (Container 1) (Box X1)